So we are at stage three, which is polishing the game, and this is where we make sure everything looks
nice by adding animations and music, sound and etc. but as I said, this is quite an exciting stage
as you get to see your game really come to life.
Now this stage can take a short amount of time or it can be a lot of time.
It all depends on how nice you want your game to look and how much you want to play.
But it's certainly true that having nice graphics and sound can go a long way to really improving your
game, so it's important to make sure you give this stage some real love.
Okay, let's get going.
Looking at this game, the first thing that I don't like is the size of the ball.
So let's make it smaller.
Yeah, let's set its size to 80%.
Right.
That looks better.
Now the second thing that needs improvement is how our main character just sort of kind of like floats
left and right while he should actually be moving his legs.
Now this is where we will really get a better understanding of costumes.
So clicking on our Ben two sprite which has the legs, I want to make it appear like his legs are moving.
So we can click on costumes.
And here the first thing we need to do is get rid of these other costumes as we don't need them and
they're just going to mess up the animation we want to create.
Now, if you right click on our first costume, you will see you can duplicate it.
Now we have two of them.
And this is where the fun world of animation begins.
So clicking on the select tool we can just select just the legs.
And below here you can see we are able to rotate the legs.
So because we want it to look like it's running we will have a shift left and then shift right.
So now for the tedious part, rotate it just a bit more to the left and center it.
Now duplicate the sprite, select the legs again, rotate them, center them and rinse and repeat.
And when we get to about this angle, we're going to start shifting the legs to the right again.
Rinse and repeat.
Now.
When the legs reach the far right, move it back one more time.
This way we have a seamless animation.
Now, although we now have the special animation, we still need the code to make it work.
So moving back to our code tab.
Yeah, we could start writing the code, or we could be smart and realize that the code for our original
bin is perfect for Ben two, so simply drag it over and then remove all these unnecessary blocks.
All we have to do now is put the next column into each of these conditional checks.
Meaning if we click left or right, it will change the costume.
So if we play the game now, notice how much better this is, how much more realistic it looks.
It shows you the power of animation.
And even if you wanted to, we could have made the body even rotate a bit.
You can give that a try if you want.
But on to the next thing, which is the ball.
And here there are a few improvements I want to make.
Firstly, I want it to play a bouncing sound when Ben hits the ball and a referee whistle when it hits
the ground.
So moving over to our sound group we can choose the start sound.
Also.
As a side note, the difference between these two is this one will play the sound until it finishes
before moving to the next code block.
Kind of like a wait block while this one won't interfere, so this one works better in our case, as
we want to ensure it doesn't interfere with our code while the sound is playing.
That's it.
If our ball touches Ben, we wanted to play the sound so we can add it here.
Next for the referee sound.
You will see we don't have it on the sprite, so we need to add it.
So going into the sound tab.
We can just click this button here and just search ref.
And here it is.
And now with it added to our sprite, you can see we can now select it in our code.
And again, logically, this should sound when our game ends.
So we can add it right here before the stop all.
Although when we play the game you might be a bit disappointed because although our ball bounce sound
works, the whistle does not.
And well, as I just said, this sound block will play until it's done, while this sound block will
play and execute the next code.
So we with a stop all is the next block.
The sound won't play all the way through, so let's switch this out for the other block.
And there you have it.
That works.
Now, with both the sounds added, the last thing I want to do for the ball is to have it look like
it is rotating in the air, instead of just like staying static like it is.
And for this, we need to go back to the costumes, but this time for the ball.
I bet you can figure this out.
So why don't you pause the video?
You've just seen what we've done already.
Pause the video and see if you can make the ball look like it's rotating.
Right.
Let me show you how you could do it if you haven't already figured it out, which I bet you did.
As you can see, we only have one costume here, so we need to make the animation ourselves.
So here, just like with our legs, we're going to need to duplicate it, then select it, rotate it
a little and select duplicate.
Rotate a little.
And I'm sure you can see where this is going.
But basically we need to keep rotating until our ball gets back to the position it started at.
So through the power of editing I'm going to fast forward this process.
But unfortunately for you this is no such fast forward process.
But it shouldn't take too long for you to continue doing this.
Well, there you have it.
As you can see, we have all these costumes that come together to form a perfect loop.
So if we go back into our code, we can easily implement this just by sticking the next costume in our
forever loop.
And when we play, look at how much more realistic this looks.
And now we're on to our last touch up.
And for this, we can move over to our backdrop and here to make the game really feel more alive.
What I want to do is animate the background by having flashing lights in the stadium.
So you know the drill.
Let's go to our backdrop.
We can delete this one.
And now this time I'm going to first duplicate the original three times.
So we have four backdrops in total.
So for the smarting light effect, it's just huge, easy to figure.
All we need to do is how this tool work allows us to create.
So what?
Then color the circle white by clicking here and dragging the slider.
And now, as you can see, we are now able to draw these white circles.
So what I'll do is cover some of these circles with white to make them look like flashing lights.
A quick tip you can zoom in by just clicking here, and you can also resize and reposition your circle.
So now I will go through each of these costumes and cover some circles just at random.
Okay.
Done.
Just like before, we can use a forever and next costume or backdrop in this case.
Okay, that's definitely a bit much.
So to make it less crazy, let's bring in a, you guessed it, a white block.
And now we can just use something small like 0.1 seconds.
That's much better.
So now for the final touch, some gay music.
And for this we can just go into the sound tab, add a new sound, and here you can choose whatever
you like, but make sure it's a loop.
For this game.
The video game two sound works all right.
Now going back to the code, we can duplicate the script because we don't want a wait statement in here
and just add the sound in and change it to Video Game two.
And that, my friends, is it.
Our game is done.
It's polished.
It's where we want it to be.
At this stage, I'm sure you can take it even further, but for now, just appreciate where it's at
and the amount of subtle detail and animations that got this to where it is.
Great work, enjoy your game and even more the fact that you are a coder.